Our goal is to generate continuous trajectories,
我们的目标是生成连续的轨迹
but how do you do that?
但是如何才能做到这一点？
Let's start with a native approach and then gets more realistic.
让我们从一个原生方法开始 然后我们会变得更加现实一点
Let's say, our car has been driving along the road at a constant speed for some time.
假设 我们的车已经沿着道路匀速行驶了一段时间
The s versus time graph is just a straight line,
在时间-速度图上 速度 s 是一条直线
since the velocity is constant,
因为速度恒定不变
and the differences time graph is flat,
在不同时间点上 图形都是平的
since the car is just staying in the center of the lane.
因为车辆一直保持在车道中间
Also note that I've shifted my axis a bit so that
另外 请注意 我把轴稍稍调整了一下
the origin of the frame is our current positioning as TNT.
这个框的原点代表我们的当前位置 TNT
This will end up being computationally efficient layer.
结束的时候 计算机显示出效率层
Now let's say we're getting off this highway soon.
现在 假设不久之后我们就会驶出这条高速
So we want to change lane in order to end up there.
因此 我们想变换车道 然后到达这里
After some delta-T which let's say it's 10 second.
在一段时间后 假设为10秒
On the SNT-graph that goal would be here and here.
在 SNT 图上 目标点将是这里和这里
The stop position and go position are fixed.
停止位和起始位都是固定的
They define what we call the boundary conditions of our trajectory at t equals zero,
它们定义了当时间 t 为0和10时
and t equals ten.
我们要生成的轨迹的边界条件
If those were our only boundary conditions,
如果这是我们全部的边界条件
then we might consider s and t-trajectory is looking like this.
那么我们只需要考虑 s 和 t 然后生成这样的轨迹
But it turns out that these aren't physically possible.
但是 事实上这些轨迹在物理上是不可行的
This kink in the slope would translate in
这个坡道上的弯折将会转化为一个瞬间的急加速
an instantaneous jumping speed which would require infinite acceleration.
这个操作需要无限大的加速度才能做到
Now, if we were to send that to our motion control module,
如果我们把这张图输入我们的运动控制模块
maybe they can track this trajectory, but probably not.
模块可能会沿着这条轨迹行进 不过很可能不会这么做
And even if they tried to track it,
如果模块试图走这条轨迹
it would result in a very strong acceleration of our car,
结果会导致车辆的急加速
which is both uncomfortable and dangerous.
这种操作会让乘客非常不适 并且很危险
This is why we need both continuity and smoothness in our trajectories.
这就是为什么我们的轨迹既要考虑连续性 又要考虑平滑性
But how much continuity and smoothness?
但是 多大的连续和平滑是可接受的？
We know we want continuity in position,
我们知道 我们需要位置上的连续
since our car cannot teleport.
因为我们的车并没有瞬间位移的技能
And it would not make sense to compute a trajectory starting 10 metres ahead of us.
如果算出的轨迹起点距我们的车10米远 那将毫无意义
And we also know that our car cannot instantaneously change speed,
我们也了解 我们的车不可能瞬间改变速度
therefore the speed should also be continuous.
因此 速度也需要连续变化
Following this logic you could also say that the acceleration should be
同样地 我们可以推出 加速度也需要连续性
continuous and maybe the acceleration's derivity as well and so on.
也许加速度的导数也是连续的
Position becomes velocity, velocity because acceleration,
从位置推出速度 从速度推出加速度
acceleration becomes jerk, and going even further you get snap, crackle, and pop.
从加速度推出急刹车 然后是 急停 急转 跳跃
It turns out that one of these quantities
事实上 这些量中的每一个
is directly related to human perception of comfort.
都直接与人的舒适感相关
So let's think about it.
我们来思考一下
In a vehicle, humans feel discomfort when which of these values is high?
这些属性中的哪一个很高时 坐在车里的乘客会感觉不舒服？
Velocity? No. When they cruise down the highway at high velocity,
速度？ 不对 因为在高速路上行驶时 人们并不会感觉到高速不舒服
people usually don't find it less comfortable than when they drive at lower speed.
相反 速度过低才让人不舒服
And if you think about airplanes,
想想飞机
they move very fast and they aren't really uncomfortable.
飞机飞得更快 但是乘客也没有不适感
Acceleration maybe?
那会是加速度？
That's slightly more tricky.
这里有点让人迷惑
We are indeed sensitive to acceleration but mostly when it becomes very high.
我们对加速度的确敏感 不过大都是在加速度很大的情况下
For example, we are all used to supporting acceleration up to
例如 我们都可以忍受高达 1G 的加速度
one G which is the most you can usually sustain in a normal car.
这是我们乘坐一般汽车的常见情况
Therefore, we shouldn't reach
因此 我们不能得出
acceleration levels that are high enough to become uncomfortable.
高加速度会导致不舒服的结论
Jerk, then? It turns out,
那么 是颠簸？
this is the quantity that humans perceive as uncomfortable.
没错 事实上 颠簸是人感觉不舒服的根源
We can tolerate high acceleration but we don't like it
我们可以接受高加速度
when our acceleration changes too quickly which is high jerk.
但是我们不能忍受加速度忽快忽慢不停变换 那就导致颠簸
So when we design trajectories for self-driving car,
因此 在我们为无人驾驶汽车生成轨迹时
we would like it, if they were jerk minimizing.
我们会着重考虑 颠簸最小化 问题